Guide to the Whitney Balliett papers, 1941-2006
Balliett. Whitney papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Whitney Balliett papers, 1941-2006
6948
Balliett
3 cubic ft.
Correspondence, photographs, printed material
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Notes, drafts, and writings on jazz criticism and biography. Also, letters to Balliett and photographs.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Whitney Balliett was esteemed jazz critic. He graduated from Cornell in 1951, and went on to write for The New Yorker. For nearly 50 years, he contributed to the publication with over 550 articles, and many more unsigned. He is known for his non-technical approach to criticism, using artful adjectives and vivid verbs to frame the music. His writing was more poetry than anything, and reading it, one will find metaphors and synesthetic synopses understandable by even the most uninformed music listener.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Notes, drafts, and writings on jazz criticism and biography. Also, letters to Balliett and photographs. The Whitney Balliett collection houses a variety of papers and correspondences from Balliett's career. There are a number of notebooks containing (nearly illegible) notes of various musician's concerts or recordings. There are also items relating to the New Yorker, including a drawing of Buddy Rich by Balliett that appeared in the magazine. Some notable letters include notes from Alice Toklas, John Updike, and Frank Sinatra. Additionally, there are a number of formerly framed items from the wall of Balliett's office.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Balliett, Whitney.; Charles, Ray, 1930-2004; Dahl, Roald; Gillespie, Dizzy, 1917-1993; Sinatra, Frank, 1915-1998; Toklas, Alice B.; Updike, John; Newport Jazz Festival
Subjects:
Jazz--History and criticism.; Jazz musicians--United States--Biography.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Misc. Papers and Notes
  - "The Thoughts of Youth" - Poems by Whitney B., March - October 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ghost Experience - Notes about Marian Johnson (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - O'Neal, Hank (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Powell, Mel (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Reviews of WB's Books (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Poetry Images... Whitney's Notes for his own Work (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "American Singers" - Book Party, November 28, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - American Academy of Artist Letters Program, May 15, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Armstrong, Louis (note from a reader) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Atlantic Monthly" Article on a 10 day QE 2 Jazz Cruise by Whitney Balliett (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Review: American Musicians (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bach, Jean (notes on "A Great Day in Harlem") (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bagneris, Vernel (original manuscript) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dearie, Blossom (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Beiderbeike, Bix (notes) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bennett, Tony (notes) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bertoncini, Gene - Moore, Michael (notes) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Blue Book Guide of the "Sporting District" in New Orleans (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Books: James Gould Cozzens Original Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Book Review: DownBeat - "Ecstasy at the Onion - 31 Pieces on Jazz by Whitney Balliett (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Book Review: "God's Perfect Child" by Caroline Fraser (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Braff, Ruby (notes) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Braff, Ruby (notes) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Briggs, Bunny (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Burns Ken (notes and piece about his Jazz series) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cain Jackie - Kral, Roy (notes on the singers Jackie + Roy) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Canney, Harry (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Canney, Harry (notes) (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Canter, Betty (notes) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Charlap, Bill (notes) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Charlap, Bill (original manuscript) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Charlap, Bill (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Charles, Ray (also Moore, Michael (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Charles, Ray (notes (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Cheatham, Doc (notes) (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Coleman, Ornette (notes) (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Cunningham, Bradley (notes) (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Davis, Miles (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Deanie, Blossom (notes) (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Eldridge, Roy (notes) (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Elliott, Bob - Goulding, Ray (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Ellis, Anita (notes) (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Feinstein, Sasha (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Finegan, Bill (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Flanagan, Tommy (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Fraishberg, Dave (notes) (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Ganner, Erroll (notes) (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Gibson, Dick: Jazz Party - Aspen, Colorado, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Gillespie, Dizzy (notes) (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - (Goodman, Benny (notes and original manuscript) (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Gordon - Research - John Gordon Piece (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Gordon, John (dealer in Americana) (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Gordon, John (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Gordon, Max (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Cafe Society, Uptown and Downtown (Murals) (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Grappelli, Stephane - Reinhardt, Django (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - The Great Hurricane of 1938, Reprint from the New Yorker, Spring 1989 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Hackett, Bobby (notes) (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Hackett, Bobby (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Hall, Jim - Charlap, Bill, March 1999 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Hall, Jim (notes) (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Hall, Jim (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Hall, Jim (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Holiday, Billie (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - New York Notes Columns' Notes (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - 365 Cedar Swamp Road Article (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - "The House and the Highway" - New Yorker, December 25, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Hurricane photos, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Keating, Cletus (Mrs.) interview for "The House and the Highway" (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Jazz Festival, Mobile notes (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Jazz Festival, Monterey notes (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Jones, Elvin (notes) (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Jones, Elvin (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Jones, Hank (notes) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Kansas City," Robert Altman Movie (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Knepper, Jimmy (notes) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Lankins, Ellis notes (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lawrence, Baby notes (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lovano, Joe (notes) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Marano, Nancy (notes and original manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - McPartland, Marian - McPartland, Jimmy (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - McPartland, Marian (notes) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Modern Jazz Quartet (notes) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Monk, Thelonious - Downbeat Score for "Straight No Chaser" (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Moore, Freddie (notes) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - New York Notes Columns (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - New York Notes (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - NY Review - E.J. Hobsbawn: Jazz Comes Back, February 12, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Moore, Michael and Charles, Ray (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Newport Jazz Festival Notes, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Newport Jazz Festival, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Newport Jazz Festival, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Playing the drums on a QE2 Jazz Cruise (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - The New Yorker, 70th Anniversary Party (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Norris, Walter - Interview, notes (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Norvo, Red (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Mercer, Mabel notes (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Mercer, Mabel (piece in Life Magazine), October 15, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Mercer, Mabel (notes) (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - McKenna, Dave (notes) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Marcus, Marie (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Moore, Michael (notes) (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Dates of Whitney Balliett's New Yorker Pieces (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Oliver, Edith (original manuscript of Edith Oliver's obituary by Balliett) (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Parker, Leon (notes) (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Powell, Mel (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Powell, Mel (notes) (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Snyder, John (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Reinhardt, Django (original manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Rowles, Jimmy (notes) (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Rich, Buddy notes (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Rich, Buddy - Drawing by Balliett which appeared in the New Yorker (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Shawn, William (Interview from Womnen's Wear Daily) (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Schueler, Jon (notes) (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Sheaming, George (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Short, Bobby notes (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Sims, Zoot - Sims, Louise (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Zutty Singleton - Modern Jazz Quartet notes (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Sloane, Carol interview notes (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Steig, Jeremy (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Syms, Sylvia (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Tate, Buddy (notes) (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Tatum, Art (notes) (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Smith, Jabbo (notes) (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Taylor, Cecil - interview notes (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Thornhill, Claude (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Torme, Mel notes (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Tough, Dave (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Venuti, Joe (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Wein, George and Joyce (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Wellstood, Dick (notes) (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Wilber, Bob (notes) (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Wilder, Joe (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Wilson, Julie - Interview Notes (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Wilson, Cassandra (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Whiting, Margaret - interviews and notes (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Collected Works (Box 2, Folder 64)
- Correspondence
  - Letters from Fans of WB's Writing (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - DownBeat - Letter to Editor - Re: Sidney Catlett (WB) (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Cooke, Alistair (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - McNulty, Faith (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Macklin, Elizabeth - "The House Style, September 29, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Maxtone - Graham, John (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Lee, Peggy (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Toklas, Alice (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Letters from: Lena Horne (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Dahl, Roald (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Dirda, Michael (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Foote, Shelby (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Hentoff, Nat (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Rowles, Jimmy (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Ondaatje, Michael (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Updike, John (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Yardley, Jonathan (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Steinman, Michael (a fan of Whitney's) (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Dance, Helen Oakley - Dance, Stanley (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Letters from: Brian McInerry - Maher, James T. (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Wilbur, Bob (letter re: Jelly Roll Morton) (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Remnick, David (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Stephenson, Sam (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Gibson, Rob (Lincoln Center) (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Letters from musicians, writers, critics, and others (including Frank Sinatra) (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Whitworth, Bill (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Reviews and quotes on WB's writing (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Turner, Frederick (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Asekoff, Louis (poet) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Letters from fans (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Letters, answered and unanswered, 1995 - 2006 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Letters, answered and unanswered, 1995 - 2006 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Letters, answered and unanswered, 1995 - 2006 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Letters, answered and unanswered, 1995 - 2006 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Lewis, John (memorial service in St. John's Cathedral, letter from a reader), 2001 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Letters from Readers (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Letter from Borclay Henry (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Letters from Cheatham, Doc - Ellis, Anita - Lewis, John (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Letters from Alex Wilder (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Photo by Jack Bradley, p. 19 - Whitney, Nancy dancing... from DownBeat magazine (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Photos of Musicians (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - The Saturday Review (pieces by WB) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Original Manuscript - City Voices: Fourteen New York Portraits (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Photographs, drawings, posters
  - Richard Avedon photograph of Duke Ellington in front of the Apollo theater, signed to Balliett with appreciation., Novebmer 30, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Henry Groskinsky photo of the members and recipients of awards ceremonial of the American Academy of Arts and Letters., May 15, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    Includes a sheet identifying all people in photo.
  - Art Kane photograph Harlem 1958 also known as A Great Day in Harlem, and recreation photograph. (Box 2, Folder 93)
    The photo depicts 57 jazz musicians. In the more modern, recreated, photo at the same location, ten of the original musicians are pictured. The photo was taken sometime before October 2003.
  - Undated photo of Ben Webster in silhouette. (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Poster for a performance, "Red Allen, Pee Wee Russell Quintet - Introduced by Whitney Balliett" Poster (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Photograph of Balliett with Duke Ellington backstage at the Monterey Jazz Festival., 1966 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Also in the photo is Nancy and Fred Seligo's date. Fred took the photo at three a.m.
  - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Includes photo of Balliett at home taken by A. Hall, a New Yorker publication with an interview and photos titled "Whitney Balliett and All That Jazz", photograph of drummer Big Sid Catlett by Skippy Adelman circa 1945.
  - Pencil drawing on paper of Whitney Balliett playing the drums by Paul Resika, January 15, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Watercolor and ink drawing for Atlantic Monthly by Barry Blitt. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    The illustration was for a piece Balliett wrote about playing the drums with a New Orleans group on a jazz cruise in November 1994, which no critics were invited on. It was a ten day voyage on the QE2 from New York City to Antigua.